[Music]
hey guys this is the first of a series
of films about the science and
psychology of polarization and it's
something that we've been working on for
quite a while I've got some really
interesting interviews with Peter Levine
Steven Porges and with Alex Evans and
it's kind of a topic that we've been
talking about quite a while generative
dialogue conversation this is kind of
delving a little bit deep more deeply
into that as a as a subject and this
introduction we're going to try and sort
of tie together the the whole series
give a sort of briefing of why we think
all these pieces fit together and also
to say what's really interesting and
I've seen to be a lot of people who are
zeroing in on this kind of area at the
moment just a couple of days ago
coincidentally I saw on Twitter that
James Lindsay and Peter Bogosian who you
may know as the academics from the
grievant Studies hoax the grievant
studies conversation putting out a new
book called how to have impossible
conversations and they've kindly sent
sent us a sort of advance copy to have a
look at it's really really interesting
and right at the beginning of that book
they say this the central thing for
generative dialogue or for genuine
conversation is psychological safety and
that's exactly what Steven Porges and
Peter Levine have been working on since
about the 60s and 70s so I think it's a
really interesting frame to bring into
this sort of more political conversation
what's exciting for me about this is
that this is something we've been
talking about since the beginning of the
channel and part of the reason that the
intellectual dark web was so interesting
you know people getting together from
different sides of the political
spectrum or you know with different
cultural values sitting to have a
long-form conversation over maybe you
know two or three hours and the promise
of that was that this was a way to
really overcome polarization and to find
a new synthesis one level is to be able
to sit down with someone and have the
conversation without attacking each
other let's say to put it in an extreme
the other level is for that conversation
to go to some new territory and I think
that for me is
a really interesting thing and so this
is one missing piece I think these these
almost like the foundations yes yes
exactly and so you know you mentioned
psychological safety there's that and
there's also a lot of other elements
that come into it and I think this is
the this is exciting but this is one of
those absolutely key elements without
which you know I don't think without
understanding the biology and the
psychology of these conversations I
don't think they can be done it's not
like a nice to have I think it's
absolutely essential I'm just gonna play
a quick clip from Steven Paul just I
wasn't gonna play until a bit later than
I play it now so I think it fits this
perfectly because he talks about better
living through neurobiology as we
understand the neurobiology of what it
is to be a human being when that becomes
our guide then culture and life becomes
better I I put on one of my slides a
couple of days ago it a kind of
modification that what DuPont the
chemical company used to say used to
advertise better living through
chemistry that was their their slogan
and what I was saying was we may be
better living through understanding
neurobiology I think it's also worth
noting this isn't just about having
difficult kind of political or cultural
conversations this is about life this is
about how do we have conversations with
each other how do we have conversations
with our partners there's that classic
phrase if you think you're enlightened
go and spend a weekend with your parents
you know it is you it's about how we
have a how we stay in our centeredness
and have conversations in general so
yeah as we've talked about like this
kind of understanding I think is the
foundation but what's really important
is sort of building from that foundation
and then what's the real world impact
and that's why it's really exciting to
have an interview with Alex Evans
so I'm gonna play a short clip from him
now because he he was government advisor
for many years he was involved in a lot
of summits around climate change and so
the big government policy and became
quite dispirited because what he
realized was all of the work of
government was talking about the
externals it was almost never talking
about the internals and so he went on a
bit of a journey around sort of
understanding polarization and learning
more and more about psychology and now
he's launching something called the
collective psychology project I mean one
of the ideas at the heart of the report
that we've just produced is the idea
that the inner and outer crises that we
see in the world and inside us are two
sides of the same coin so on the one
hand you have this sort of pile of
crises out there in the world like
climate breakdown and hyper inequality
and mass extinction and so on and then
over here you've got this pile of mental
health crises like suicide and self-harm
and anxiety and depression and addiction
and so on and so on and what I'm arguing
in the report is that at the moment you
know these two sets of crises are
fueling each other we feel messed up
inside partly because we feel like the
world is messed up out there and when we
feel messed up inside when we're kind of
triggered we act out in ways that worsen
the state of the world so again it's
another example of a feedback loop now
you look at mainstream politics as it is
today or for that matter the kind of
campaigning that you get from big global
NGOs it only talks about the outer stuff
it's all about you know issues in the
world of out there and it's just silent
on the question of the states of mind of
the citizens who are voting or the
policymakers who are making the decision
it's sort of you know they're just
completely separate so one of the things
I find particularly interesting not just
about what Alex was saying but about
this entire topic is that there's lots
of different levels to it you know so
alex is talking about you know
government tends to look at the system's
level but needs to also look at the
individual level and those two things
are you know it says two sides of the
same coin and then there's the
biological level of understanding where
my biology is while I'm doing it so
there's all these different layers to it
and I think what seems to be happening
right now is lots of people are coming
in from different angles and hopefully
and what's very interesting is what does
the synthesis look like and what is it
and how do we take that synthesis and
use it practically in our kind of
day-to-day lives so it's really
fascinating to see the journey that Alex
had been on from a completely different
starting point the starting point of
like politics and systems change when I
was chatting with him he had exactly the
same reference points that we're
familiar with from our
counseling training polyvagal theory
somatic experiencing Peter Levine Steven
Porges all of this stuff and they were
there like in a waste of like superstars
in the counseling and and in particular
in the trauma world because they were
the ones that really understood how the
body stores emotions and how the body
trap and how the body metabolizes
experience and this this kind of work is
just I think absolutely crucial to bring
into the mainstream bring into the the
sort of political and the conflict world
an understanding that especially now and
more and more under the influence of
social media and under the influence of
kind of ever-expanding and
ever-increasing pace of life we're all
in some sort of low-level overwhelm a
lot of the time or a lot of us are so
this kind of work becomes essential to
navigating those kind of spaces and we
were lucky enough to get an interview
with Peter Levine when we were out in
America recently if you're talking to
two people who are in the hyper-vigilant
State the sympathetic adrenal state or
the shut down state even more so you
can't engage with them because you
perceive them either as threat or as
mortal threat because your nervous
system is stuck in that groove and so
there's no way you can really listen to
another person and and express yourself
so they want to listen to you while
you're in one of these stuck States you
have to be able to come into the social
engagement system could you talk about
like the physiology of this like what is
actually going on when we're in these
conflicts with each other and when
because well I also understand is that
we stop listening to each other at a
certain point the polyvagal theory gives
us a very clear map of exactly how that
works and what it looks like you can see
the facial expression when somebody's in
fight or foot they're mobilizing the jaw
and the neck is tight when somebody's in
a state of social engagement the eyes
are relaxed and open this part of the of
the the face is is the one that's more
active or the one in more engage okay so
when you're feeling like this
you will not be able to feel like this
so so again we read signals from each
other's faces from each other's postures
and if we consciously subconsciously all
the time we all do it we may not be
aware that we're doing but we're all
doing and referencing back to something
that a lot of the sort of more avid fans
of the channel will be aware of Jordan
green hall and his kind of concept of
broadcast versus digital and discernment
what that does that puts a huge amount
of impact on the individual which is why
individual sort of regulation and and
our own psychology and our own biology
becomes so much more important and you
notice how much of a burden is placed on
the individual now it's not like the
broadcast modality where most of your
agency is limited to a very narrow band
and you're really relying on the causal
structure that you're embedded in to do
almost all the work in the decentralized
collective intelligence for to actually
work almost all of the agency is
actually on the individuals you have to
have really really effective responsible
individuals and by responsible what I
mean is they're they're able to respond
to the environment in the way that I'm
talking about they're not reacting so I
think one important thing to add to that
is that while it starts with the
individual it doesn't stop with the
individual so you know Jordan Hall talks
about this concept of sovereignty and
you know what you were describing kind
of coming into our own agency and our
own discernment so we can start making
sense of the world but we have to make
sense of our world with one another so
we have to find a way not only to be
sovereign in ourselves but to be open
and contact full with one another and to
figure out okay how together can we be
in a mode where we're starting to make
sense of the world better than one of us
could by ourselves so to come back to
Alex Evans and the collective psychology
project a lot of his work he did in in
Israel he went to live in Israel for a
while and just saw how in Israel in
particular everyone is in a state of
low-level hyper-vigilance at all times
on both the Palestinian side and the
Israeli side and how that affects
politics there and how it makes things
very very difficult because if you're in
a hyper vigilant state it's very
difficult not to
to be in a sort of fight-or-flight
response and see the other as an enemy
it's almost impossible and he then draws
parallels with what's been happening in
the in the UK in the US when I play
another quick clip from his interview I
took a sabbatical for six months and
went to live in Jerusalem with my family
for that period and obviously the
political polarization there is even
more extreme and at one level that was
incredibly depressing and I could see
the kind of similarities with brexit or
with Trump's America I mean obviously
it's more extreme in Israel and
Palestine but nevertheless I felt like
it was on the same spectrum in some
sense but what was hopeful when I was
there was finding the work of a few
psychologists people like Gina Ross who
are arguing that really to understand
polarization there you can't divorce it
from its mental health context
particularly the fact that continuous
traumatic stress which is a bit like
post-traumatic stress disorder when it's
not post when it's just an everyday
ongoing reality but of course that
catalyzes polarization because the
classic symptoms of continuous traumatic
stress are things like anxiety and hyper
vigilance and especially other ring kind
of projecting everyone onto some
idealized shadowy other and when enough
individuals display these symptoms of
course they start to manifest
politically - and you know of course the
the other reality there is that people
live in this constant low-level state of
threat perception I mean Israelis are
constantly at some level perceiving
threats of terrorism or of rocket
attacks or even of invasion and then
Palestinians are constantly perceiving
the threat of arbitrary arrests or of
their house being the next to be
demolished or of just living in kind of
conditions of more or less total
surveillance so everyone's triggered all
of the time and then you know I mean at
another level you look at that and you
think well I can see how this plays out
in a kind of conflict zone like this but
actually is it is it overreaching a bit
to say that this is also relevant to
brexit or to trump and of course I'm not
saying that you know most voters in
Britain
the states are traumatized in the SIS
trick'd medical sense but the threat
perception absolutely shows up when you
look at opinion polling of why do people
vote Trump one of the strongest
predictors for that was this sense that
the American Way of life is threatened
it was the same with leave voters in the
UK many of whom clear majority of whom
agreed like you know Britain
increasingly feels like a foreign
country and that makes me feel
uncomfortable
so there's threat perception on that
side and then of course as soon as
you've had the presidential election in
2016 or the brexit referendum all the
kind of liberal cosmopolitan
internationalists type people also wake
up feeling like they're living in a
foreign country and that makes them feel
very uncomfortable now you know how it
feels right and so the threat perception
is contagious and this is the big risk
that it becomes a kind of self
amplifying feedback loop and so one of
the questions right at the heart of the
collective psychology project is well
how would we reverse the polarity of
that feedback loop so instead of you
know these kind of mutually reinforcing
you know threat perceptions across the
political spectrum we have a kind of
mutual reinforcing process of sort of
healing and coming back together to a
sense of empathy for each other and
respect for each other's experiences and
how we reach the values that we've got
and so on I mean my only concern with
that narrative is that it can seem
almost condescending because you're sort
of saying and when we talk about these
things when we talk about Trump we talk
about brexit as being only a product of
sort of fear it can sound like more of
the liberal elite kind of thinking well
we know better than you what why you've
done something how do you avoid that in
the narrative around this kind of
ionization well I think I mean as I say
I think the issue of threat perception
is by no means confined to one side of
the political spectrum I think on the
contrary is something that sort of
cropping up here there and everywhere
but I mean of course you know you can
look at for instance membership to the
European Union and make a completely
trenchant critique of the EU on very
solid rational basis that has nothing to
do with threat perception or fear or
anything like that and I would as it
happens by a lot of that critique myself
there's much about the EU that needs
reforming but I think when you look at
the state of our
it'll debate and how much kind of
triggering there is and how much just
heat and you know projection there is in
the discourse there's something deeper
going on here as well yeah he mentions
Jeana Ross who's an expert in this field
and has been working particularly with
conflict for a long time who I caught up
with the other day so when you think
about it people are approaching the
resolution of conflict and a very
rational reasonable manner but where is
the attention to the emotional
foundation and these are the aspects
that are not being addressed when people
are trying to come up with very rational
intelligent cogent solutions for
problems but the emotions don't care
about that if I don't feel safe I don't
care how reasonable your solution needs
seems to be that's not going to affect
me so what I then saw that was very very
important was to really marry that you
feel together so I developed a protocol
actually that combines the two on an
ongoing basis the whole time it's one of
the keywords for me is curiosity and
it's a it's a really interesting word
because it means when when we're curious
we accept the idea that we don't know
the answer but there's a there's a
there's a kind of natural ability to be
open when we're curious and one of the
lightbulb moments on a recent course
that was actually a breathwork course
where they were talking about polyvagal
theory and somatic experiencing was
where they started using that word
curious and was saying that it's
impossible to be curious and defensive
at the same time which is a really
important thing and that I think fits
into the nature of like any kind of
generative conversation is about
curiosity you can't be curious and
traumatized at the same time the
physiology that doesn't allow them to
both be there so if you can get the
client enlist the client and being
curious about their sensations and and
and images and feelings then you've
gotten halfway there I think there's a
useful link from the world of kind of
meditation research here as well there's
a this woman called Shauna Shapiro who's
done a lot of studies on meditation she
talks about its three elements its
attitude attention and intention I think
it applies very closely to staying
curious you know it's it's very easy to
be knocked off into thinking I know or I
disagree with that I'm just waiting for
this person to shut up so I can jump in
and put my point across
often in meditation is called a kind of
a soft alertness and that's it that's a
skill to cultivate because it doesn't
just come naturally to any of us to any
human being and you know you have to
kind of literally engage your prefrontal
cortex so that you can stay present and
stay with it so it's a it's kind of a
for me it's kind of a dance between
psychology and biology that's that's a
constant process and you get better and
better at it the more you practice it
the other interview we've got with one
of the pioneers in this field is with
Steven Porges and Steven Paul just came
up with polyvagal theory independently
of Peter Levine but when Peter Levine
and Steven Paul just met they
immediately connected because polyvagal
theory validated and explained what
Peter Levine was seeing in his practice
so Peter Levine was having these
understandings and realizations about
how emotion and trauma was stored in the
body and realizing that a lot of the
time physic the body was intimately
connected with what we normally consider
psychology and polyvagal theory
basically grounded that in neurobiology
and it works primarily on the vagus
nerve the vagus nerve is the longest
nerve in the body it comes from the
brain and goes to all of the major
organs it also goes to the face and what
polyvagal theory explains is firstly how
we're constantly getting information
from our from a gut and from our heart
and a heart is actually connected to our
face and we're also then connected to
other people through that so we're
constantly regulating a nervous system
in relation to other people and in
relation to what's going on inside
polyvagal theory has several features or
goes
few of them the important the first
important one is that it gives us a way
of organizing our own bodily reactions
and it really emphasizes that the norm
which merely means the brain regulation
of the autonomic nervous system the
neural system that regulates the the
organs within our body followed an
evolutionary tradition trajectory so we
had a very primitive autonomic system
that really was about maintaining
metabolic resources so it was very much
oriented in if there was enough oxygen
in the food it just kind of shut us down
okay then with evolution from these
ancient vertebrates that had only won a
very ancient old vagal circuit and that
old vagal circuit was unmyelinated and
myelination is really the fatty
substance that coats a nerve and if it's
myelinated it could actually convey
these signals more efficiently and more
specifically but in the very ancient
vertebrates they only had this older
dorsal vagal system but we still have it
it's the primary system that still goes
to our gut and the major defense
response of that the autonomic nervous
system for these ancient vertebrates was
basically shutting down immobilizing
death fainting through evolution a
sympathetic nervous system came onboard
and that one was a spinal sympathetics
that came on with the bony fish and you
can see them moving and even stopping so
now you have an autonomic pounce of
mobilization through the sympathetic
nervous system and immobilization that
old Vegas and then what you have with
mammals and this is the interesting part
of polyvagal theory something strange is
something a miraculously occurs
with the transition from the ancient as
stinked extinct reptiles to mammals and
that is you have a newer vagal circuit
that's bile in it that helps calm or
coordinate these the older veil circuit
to support homeless stasis and to enable
some things to work without getting you
into fight or flight but the other
miraculous part is that the area of the
brain that regulates that pathway the
vagus is not the same that regulates the
old Vegas going to the gut it's linked
to the nerves in the area the brainstem
is linked to the part that regulates the
nerves they regulate your face the
muscles of your face and head it
regulates your social engagement system
your ingest of system the way you touch
and connect with the world so it's
really this kind of remarkable
transition where our heart became
connected in a normal way to the the
nerves that regulate our voice the
intonation of our voice our facial
expressions and even our ability to
extract information by listening so
there are muscles in our middle ear to
our facial expressivity and the
intonation of our voice
so now we project our heart in our voice
and people know that intuitively they
respond that way we project our feelings
in our face so these become the
important parts of how we make
connections with others but the by
directionality so that we're in a sense
of a person is in a physiological
destabilized way their voice is very
different and we often for a good
therapist or good human beings and good
parents or good teachers we know that
and we calm them and how do we calm them
it's not the words that are powerful
it's how we use the words it's the
intonation of our voice so polyvagal
theory emphasizes these evolutionary
stages but also emphasizes that under
challenge under demands that the illness
or threat our autonomic nervous system
shifts state it moves from this social
engagement safe state
we are connected with others it moves to
defensive states and how we're also then
transmitting our own internal state
through our voice and through our face
to other people and how important that
is for what they call Co regulation so
regulating ourselves in relation to
other people and how does this theory or
theoretical framework apply to say
conflict and mediation well it defines
conflict doesn't in terms of that we've
conflict so people feel that there is a
threat or their bodies feel as a threat
to have remediation you have to provide
sufficient cues of safety so that you
now get into a dialogue now our dialogue
by nature of being the word implies some
reciprocity in the interaction and when
you do wrestle we have reciprocity into
action you have a listening component as
well as expressive component so you have
a witnessing component so it part of I I
think the major issue of conflict is
that people don't listen to each other
so they're not witnessing and if people
don't listen to you when you try to talk
express something or let's say you're
even a child and you're not being
listened to what happens to your
physiological state will you become very
uncomfortable you become frustrated and
as you get older with those same
feelings you become angry and
belligerent and so we have to understand
that being listened to being witnessed
not necessarily being agreed with but
being witnessed and appreciated for what
you're saying is really part of our
birthright it's something that we scream
to do have and polarization is occurs
when people aren't listened to they're
not witnessed and they feel marginalized
just to join that together with the
polyvagal and kind of real or genuine
conversation is because what polyvagal
theory shows is that either we're in an
open
a frame of mine we're in what they call
the ventral vagal circuit where where
we're able to connect with others we're
able to take in new information we're
able to be curious or were in a
defensive frame of mind and when we're
in a defensive frame of mind where we're
pretty much unavailable and that shift
can happen quite quickly that shift can
happen very quickly even in a
conversation where and developing that
awareness of when we're slipping into a
defensive frame of mind and when we're
slipping into and one we're more open
and then hacking that neurology or
hacking that physiology is going to be
an important or essential thing for us
to learn to have these conversations and
I think a key point here is that these
are skills and let's say a way of being
that we have to practice and cultivate
rather than something that we can decide
on the intellectual level okay I'm going
to drop into the having that next time I
have a conversation with with my partner
or someone I disagree with on Facebook
I'm gonna just drop into this no that's
that's not how it works we need to
really cultivate these skills and I
think someone who's been doing that
extensively and with with success is
Jamie Weil who we've put out a few
interviews with and had one quite
recently on the channel as well and I
think it's very interesting to hear him
talk about what actually happens when
you're getting people into groups and
getting people into flow what are some
of the things some of the practical
techniques we can use to actually you
know practice these skills because we're
in a culture of the moment or the
conversation just keep seeming to break
down again and again and again and this
kind of understanding like the
neurophysiology of coherence or the
neurophysiology of connection seems
really vital in that do you what's your
take on that yeah I mean I would almost
I mean short answer is yes because
there's no there's no opportunity for
tribal primates to be in coherence
without that also having a you know
showing up in the kind of stack of our
bodies and brains for sure so for what
we want is the ability to have a nice
conversation together the ability for us
to have that nice conversation sits on
the foundation alright of bodies and
brains and hearts and minds in
achievement and whether that's simple
things like mirror neurons or it's more
complicated things like overall new roof
is new ro physiological
that is for sure another lever for us to
play with so you know the business
school II Sade in Spain that we wrote
about in the stealing fire the idea that
they took a strategic business problem
and had a bunch of MBA students try and
solve it together you know with one-way
mirrors and biometrics tracking them on
all this kind of stuff and they figured
out who are the emergent leaders in this
group and and they backed out
statistically you know how much people
talk how loudly people talked the words
they used even what they actually had to
say about solving the problem none of
that stuff was statistically as
significant as the fact that that those
leaders those emergent leaders couldn't
regulate their own nervous systems and
do it in a way that entrained other
people into their states so it's a
little bit like that old story of you
know Galileo entering the watchmakers
shop and seeing you know all the all the
clocks on the wall swinging in time with
the one with the longest pendulum so
that idea of the longest pendulum and
trains all the others into that field
that to me has been my inquiry really on
the sort of biohacking spaces what's the
longest pendulums in our bodies if we
had to pick and there's a good jillion
things we can map track measure from
brain waves to heart rate to heart rate
variability to new chemistry to posture
to respiration to Africa you know get
all sorts but what are the one or two or
three that if you get those right the
entire rest of our bodies and brains
cascades into coherence and then that's
a strong signal that's now that's
lengthened our pendulum and now we are
far more likely to bring others into
that coherent state and so before we get
to kind of what we know you might call
communitas or like a highly coherent
group presencing something greater than
the sum of the parts
if you find yourself in an attempt to
have a coherent conversation meaning
we're trying to do something that none
of us know what's gonna come of this but
if we play it right something better
than any one of us separately could've
thought us I let's say that's the kind
of a version of the game we're playing
and things start to go sideways right
somebody gets hijacked somebody starts
engaging an older less functional
pattern you feel triggered you want to
react you know that's where that right
there the first moment is you know this
this is man's search for meaning right
it's that it's the stimulus in the
response and the space between what's
happening and my reaction to it therein
lies freedom and redemption so a couple
of things and this is you know granny
wisdom 101 which is if you're about to
get angry or say something off the cuff
take a deep breath good it actually
takes several deep breaths and
specifically engage in you know what
freedivers called vagal tone breathing
which is just the idea of act like a
ten-second exhale with a two-second hole
so exhale fully empty your lungs
once your lungs are completely empty
hold them for two seconds and then just
fill your lungs and you can do that at a
table you don't need to announce it you
can just actually use that and just take
five of those and you will match it in
fact if you do it a friend of ours as a
neuroscientist at Stanford his name's
Andrew Huberman and he's done
fascinating research where if you
combine I gaze so if you kind of go soft
focus meaning that you're focusing your
eyes to the outside of your frame and
you do that vagal nerve breathing so the
super-slow exhales a whole inhale and
you do it through your nose you
completely draw your physiological
threat response you just chill the
out super fast and so that would be the
simplest and people might think you're
just kind of spaced out
oh cool you're not there but yeah if you
can just go soft soft I focus so you're
not laser focused and you're not focused
on something immediately in front of you
and you do nitrogen basically nasal
exhales then that will really calm you
down further the next would be and part
of the reason for the nose breathing the
Carolyn's the Karolinska Institute in
Sweden has done some fascinating
research on nitric oxide and that
correlates with some research at Harvard
that basically said nitric oxide is a
neurotransmitter and it's a gaseous
molecule and it takes stress response
stuff out of our brain it shunts it all
the way and it brings in feelings of you
know bliss I even call it the Bliss
molecule right so basically anything you
can do in your body to increase nitric
oxide is usually a good thing for stress
response and resilience all right so
that was the Hobbit research then the
Karolinska Institute has found that
nasal breathing increases it three to
five times and that if you really want
to get freaky vibrating your nasal
cavity as you breathe out through your
nose oh hmm something like that or if
you were playing a didgeridoo or playing
a clarinet or a Champa and I actually
increases the nitric oxide production
15 times so if you slam all these
together you're like okay I'm gonna
breathe I'm gonna exhale slowly through
my nose with visual focus to the
periphery and I might depending on my
social situation of my comfort level
even hum as I do it that is actually
gonna calm me down and give me a reset
so that's a true straight up kind of
biohack I don't need to think anything
to do it just do it and it will have
some positive effect the next is now a
bridge
what's the bridge between
neurophysiology and psychology and then
even higher level judo would be I'm not
trying to fix it
change it shape it at all I'm simply
gonna notice it and name it and with a
little bit of practice I can speak with
that truth into the shade conversation
and quite often you'll find out you you
find it the whole thing can draw to the
level where oh me too or oh thank you
for saying that and then we're back to
that level of resonance and coherence
not from follow me I'm super stoked this
is all amazing and I'm gonna be this
bright light it's more like actually
let's actually orient around what is
happening right now now what are the
truths we can explore if we can stay in
this place together without judgment
without naming the emotion without then
creating the narrative without enacting
triggered drama responses around it and
that actually is arguably an even more
magic place for us to get together to
forge coherence which is wherever the
hell we actually are versus some effort
to escape it fix it mend it transcend it
my sense I think is that this is still
quite cutting edge maybe marginal but
it's definitely the conversations
definitely moving in that direction and
that's where I'm really interested
personally that's where I'm always
interested string conversation and where
is something that's just on the fringe
of it but it looks very promising
psychedelics for example for the last
six or seven years I've been looking at
journalistically and thinking okay that
it will shift there will be mainstream
interest in this now house then we're
now in what we've called kind of the new
psychedelic Renaissance
there's definitely mainstream interest
and I think mainstream interest in the
site like sort of collective psychology
and therefore the kind of neurobiology
of all of this stuff is coming I mean
this sort of so it's interesting to look
at what what has kept this out of the
mainstream conversation for so long
there's a few different factors I think
a lot of it is based in this kind of
Cartesian dualism Descartes classic sort
of split in the 16th 17th century of
splitting mind and matter and that's had
a huge impact - ever since of seeing all
of these things as separate but there's
there's a new holism and there's a new
kind of understanding of how these
things fit together how the body is
intrinsically involved in in the mind
for example which is what all of this
work is it's bringing back into
psychology and then also then psychology
being intimately involved in in the in
the political world and in any kind of
policy changes yeah I think that that
for me is one of the big things is that
that Cartesian dualism and the way it
plays out in culture and the way that
just through our education through even
our language we are much more
comfortable with what we know and what
we don't know and much more comfortable
being in this kind of disembodied
intellectual space often then in the
more liminal flowing let's say chaotic
space in McGilchrist
is got a really great model of this for
anyone who's interested we've got a few
interviews in the channel with him you
know you've done great work around
looking at the left brain and the right
brain which is a lot more complex than
just left brain logical and right brain
kind of creative as
people used to think but ironically
there is actually some truth in that as
well and so he argues in part that we're
in a very left brain dominated society
so it's very much the left brain is
focused in part on what we know what we
know we know whereas the right brain is
focused in part on what we don't know
and so that you know we've talked quite
a few times on the channel around having
conversations that are more liminal so
that means that they're more in a space
of not knowing and again that concept of
curiosity comes up you know curiosity
inherent in the idea of curiosity as I
don't know because if you knew you
wouldn't be curious and so there is a
biological again a biological aspect to
it there's a cognitive aspect to it and
there's a cultural aspect to it and
there is a shift happening in that and I
think all these speakers are part of
that shift so yeah on that subject of
how this has being so kind of not
included in the mainstream perspective
for so long I spoke to a guy called
Steve Haines who I've experienced I've
done a couple of his courses really
really interesting bodywork who knows
this stuff really inside out ability to
feel is fundamental to how our mind
works so cognition memory and emotion
are rooted in a readout of our
physiological state and I'm offering
here through the most of this interview
is that our physiological state it's
primarily am i safe and if I'm not safe
I go fight or flight or freeze so if
that's happening my feelings that inform
my mental state of cognition my memory
and my emotional state will be colored
by the fact I've got this danger
physiology running inside me so to
embrace that means embracing the
messiness of what was historically
hysterical emotional states in the body
that weren't doctor spot fantasy of a
rational human being who would analyze
and realize and work out what we're
really doing is sort of feeling and
attaching to things that feel right so
an idea is valid because it's elegant
and somehow it tastes right it smells
right or it my body can ease into that
state because those numbers fit together
in
elegant way the feeling is the root of
rationality rather rationality mind and
pure thought being this separate sort of
special entity that was a purview of
psychiatrists it's a much messier
embodied place and feelings are central
to the whole process of consciousness
yeah and it's really interesting and
exciting that quite a few of the people
from very different backgrounds have the
same sense that things are moving in
this direction then it might be an idea
whose time has come but what we're not
seeing is that synthesis of recognizing
that you know our mental health our
state of mind
matter for the state of the world and
vice versa but I think that's partly
because this isn't an idea that's really
surfaced much until recently and now it
feels like a lot of people are
converging on to this territory I mean I
don't feel at all like the collective
psychology projects the only player in
this space I think a ton of people are
sort of converging on this space which
gives me a lot of hope that feels like
this is something that's kind of ripe
that's ready to you know mature and take
root in the world and I think therefore
like you know I don't see this as like
expecting massive pushback from people
who work in politics on this stuff I
think that it's just a question if we
have to figure out how to start seeding
it so it can take regions Brown we are
connected species and if we don't
appreciate that we are in a sense
injuring the species and we have to take
on the responsibility the bottom line is
I think there are gonna be more and more
people having this understanding because
now you have with polyvagal theory and
neurobiology that supports the
philosophy LOF achill and for many
people even a spiritual religious view
so you have a convergence of different
orientations all ending up in the same
point this is really embryonic work we
have no idea what's actually gonna fly
what are going to be the interventions
that can really have a transformational
impact and go to scale I think the
larger question is how do we create
systems and platforms for lots of little
experiments many of them very small
scale of
logo and from making sure we share the
learning from those experiments among a
kind of involving community of people
who feel like they are practitioners of
collective psychology so that when we
fail we do it quickly and we make sure
that as many people as possible have
access to the lessons from that failure
so hopefully this film has kind of tied
the topic together made sense of it and
also made you want to go and watch the
other films the whole films so we're
gonna release them over the next couple
of weeks if you want to get early access
to see them all now you can become a
supporter and they're in the members
area of the website so subscribe also
sign up for notifications just click the
bell button below if you want to make
sure that you get notified when those go
online and also we're gonna be running
events in London over the autumn yeah
we're gonna be doing something a little
bit different this autumn so we're gonna
have a series of events where we're
really trialing and growing let's say a
protocol of how do we actually get into
these conversations and how do we do it
sustainably in a way that could be
replicated potentially in different
cities so where it's quite exciting you
know so we're gonna be announcing that
soon it's gonna be quite a few they're
gonna be focused on different practices
techniques and we're hoping to build a
core group of people who really want to
kind of go to the edge I guess and then
kind of level up in a new way
see you saying rebel wisdom is a new
sense making platform bringing together
the most rebellious and inspiring
thinkers from around the world if you're
enjoying our content then you can help
us make more by becoming a subscriber
which will give you access to a load of
exclusive films also you can then join
our group zoom calls to discuss the
ideas in the films and you can send us
ideas for questions for upcoming
interviews we're also looking for
talented people to help us out with
editing graphics music that kind of
thing and if you're a regular viewer
you'll know we talk a lot about the
value of embodying or actually living
out the ideas that we talk about so
that's why we run regular events in
London check out the links on the
website for more and hope to see you
soon
you